<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The christians mourning garment</title>
            <author>Worship, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848512</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13612</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13612)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1674:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The christians mourning garment</title>
                  <author>Worship, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop at the entrance into the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Worship.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div rend="roman" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIANS MOVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING GAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.</p>
            <p>The third Edition.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi rend="italic">Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the entrance into the Exchange. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable and virtuous young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, <hi rend="italic">Henry,</hi> Lord <hi rend="italic">Haſtings,</hi> Grace and peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIght Noble Impe.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THoſe little creatures the Silk-wormes, ſhunning duality of meates, and betak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues wholy to the freſh leaſage of the Mulberie tree, frame (by Natures inſtinct and vertue of the Plant) ſo faire, and ſo ſweet a webbe, that the greateſt perſonage will not thinke much to weare it. I am the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the ſeruants of God, farre leſſe than the leaſt of his mercies: yet by the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his bleſſed ſpirit (the ſoule of my ſoule) and the efficacie of his holy word (whereon alone I wiſh to feede) I truſt I haue ſhaped ſuch a garment as the beſt Chriſtian will not diſdaine to put on. A Mourning Garment it is: For lighter colours beſeeme not Gods Childe in this careleſſe Age, where Ladye Faith goes bare-foote (alas) all alone, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by no good workes, which makes her waſh handkerchers in her teares.</p>
            <p>I preſent this veſture to your Lordſhip, not
<pb facs="tcp:13612:3"/> doubting but you will accept it, and adorne your ſelfe with it. And I deſire it may be a token of a dutifull and thankfull minde, for the numberleſſe fauours our happy vnhappy name hath receiued from your moſt noble, and for zeale of religion moſt worthie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors.</p>
            <p>The Lord bleſſe your Honor, that as you growe in ſtature, and yeares, ſo you may growe in grace and fauouor with God, and men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all obſeruance, William Worſhip.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:3"/>
            <head rend="roman">The Chriſtians mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Garment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a rule that will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the tutch-ſtone, <hi rend="roman">No man comes to heauen with drie eyes.</hi> Our ſelues are ſhippes laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched foorth for heauen: our teares muſt be the ſea, our ſighes the gales of winde, while <hi rend="roman">Hope</hi> is the anchor, and <hi rend="roman">Grace</hi> ſteares the helme. <hi rend="roman">Moſes, Hezekiah, Peter, Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> and all the Saints of God were waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the riuers that guſht from their own eyes to the kingdome of glory.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, though euery penitent ſinner wéepe, yet euery one that wéepes is not a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinner. For teares in themſelues are but things indifferent, &amp; neuer pleaſe God, but when they iſſue from a troubled ſpirite, ſuppled with grace, and wounded with true remorſe, and ſence of ſinne. It is not ſorrow, <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 10.</note> but godly ſorrow that goes for currant.</p>
            <p>Some wéepe for themſelues, not for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſome wéepe for others not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſome neither wéepe for themſelues, nor others: ſome both wéepe for themſelues and others. To wéepe for thy ſelfe, not for
<pb facs="tcp:13612:4"/> others betokens luke-warmneſſe: to wéepe for others, not for thy ſelfe, hypocriſie: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wéepe for thy ſelfe, nor others, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hart: both to wéepe for thy ſelfe, and others, zealouſneſſe. The laſt of theſe is an effect of holy ſorrow, which who ſo findeth not in himſelfe one time, or other, is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a veſſell of wrath.</p>
            <p>In the name of God then, good Chriſtian brother, let thine eyes ſpout out teares as a Conduite ſpouteth out waters, for thy grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, capitall, and enormous vices. Say not thou art Sanguine complexiond and canſt not wéepe, of a manly ſtomack and wilt not <note place="margin">Sam. 1. 16. 12.</note> wéepe, for <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> was both, yet teares were his meate, day and night. Flatter not thy ſelfe: the vaine conceit of eaſie attaining ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation may caſt many a ſoule away in a yeare. Thou muſt vpon neceſſity mortifie the fleſh: Away with it, Away with it, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, crucifie it. Now ere thou can do this, it will coſt thée many a groane, and many a teare, oh it will go to the hart of thée.</p>
            <p>As thou tendreſt thy ſoule, looke home: vnrip, vnbowell, ranſacke thy ſelfe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. Mourne for thy originall ſinnes, and for thy actuall ſinnes, for thy ſinnes before thy calling, and ſince thy calling: for thy preſumptuous ſinnes, and for thy ſinnes of
<pb facs="tcp:13612:4"/> infirmitie, for thy open ſinnes, and for thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſinnes, for thy ſinnes of ommiſſion, and for thy ſinnes of commiſſion. Stéepe thine eyes in teares, read letters of diſcomfort on the ground as thou goeſt, let the ſtreames of thy ſighes, and the incenſe of thy praiers riſe vp like mountaines before the Lord, and if this will not mooue him to pitty, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible wéepe teares of bloud.</p>
            <p>Aboue all things beware thou looke not ſowerly in company to be ſéene of men, for then thy rewarde is ſure to be great in hell. Get thée into thy moſt retyred cloſet, let no body (by thy good will) know of it, pull the latch into thée ſée there be no holes in the dore, no cranies nor clifts in the wall, &amp; then fall groueling to the earth, thump thy breſt, ſtrike vpon thy thigh, wring thy hands, and poure out thy ſoule before the Lorde: ſo he that ſéeth thy true humiliation in ſecret, ſhal one day rewarde thée openly in the ſight of his glorious Angels.</p>
            <p>Vnclaſpe thy Bible, lay the ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements before thée, and (bedewing them with thy teares) make thine humble confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thus before God.</p>
            <p>O my God, I am confounded, and aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to lift vp mine eyes vnto thée, my God, for mine iniquities are increaſed, and my
<pb facs="tcp:13612:5"/> treſpaſſe is growne vp into heauen. Yet Lord remember thy mercies of olde, and open mine eyes that I may ſée the wonders of thy law, that ſo ſinne may be out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 12</note> ſinful. Good God, thy commandements are iuſt, and holy, but I am carnall, ſold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne, and ſhould not lye yelping, and howling in the burning lake of damned ſoules, if I had my right. Bleſſed be thy name for inſpiring this good motion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating in thy law, for it is a glaſſe wherein I may beholde the vglye morphew of my ſoule, and ſo be forced to flée to my redéemer for his precious blood, to rinſe, and munditie me, that I may be preſented a ſpotleſſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin before thée.</p>
            <p>Alas, I ſhould haue béene thy <hi rend="roman">Nazarite,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The 1. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and haue giuen thée all my hart: but I haue giuen the fleſh a péece of it, the worlde a péece of it, and the deuill a péece of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I ſhould haue worſhipped thée according to the ſquare, and tenor of thy word, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding, detracting, changing: but I haue ballanced thy ſeruice after mine owne ſcoales, and haue more delighted in falling downe before a gilt Image, than in behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſwéet ſonne moſt liuely crucified in <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note> thy worde preached, and ſacraments admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I ſhould haue magnified thy name, and haue ſpoken of it with high reuerence: but I (ah wretch) haue curſt &amp; band, and cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 10.</note> Ieſu in my mouth, at whoſe bleſſed name euery knée ſhould bow, both of things in heauen, and things in earth, and things vnder the earth, yea Lord I haue torne thy holy name, as the Draper raſheth out a péece of linnen to the buyer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I ſhould haue hallowed the beſt daye of the ſeauen, and haue beſtowed it in prayer, hearing of Sermons, receiuing the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, almes, meditation on Gods workes, but I (woe worth me for it) haue moſt vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanouſly prophaned it. It hath béene a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnto me, by barring me from triuiall ſports. Yea I thought my ſelfe an holy man, when I ſat ſtill at home and did nothing, though while I did ſo, the beaſt at the cribbe kept as good a ſabboath as I.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I ſhould haue béene ſubiect to the higher <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1</note> powers ordained of thée: I ſhould haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured my parents, thy inſtruments for my life and education: and I ſhould haue béene ready (with the <hi rend="italic">Galathians)</hi> to haue pluckt <note place="margin">Gal. 4 15</note> out mine eyes to haue done the Preachers good: but I (a ſinfull worme of fiue foot long) haue ſpoken euill of the Magiſtrate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be the ſtaffe of my Parents age. As
<pb facs="tcp:13612:6"/> for the Miniſters, I euer held them for a ſort of ſimple ſoules, the very ſcorne of men, and outcaſt of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> I ſhould haue loued my neighbour déerly, and haue wincked at wrong, not letting the ſunne go downe vpon my wrath: but I (this one thing were inough to ſtanche the blood of my dying Lord) haue boyled in rage for one tart word, and for a ſmall iniurie haue wilfully and ſtubbornly refuſed the bleſſed Sacrament of thy ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> I ſhould in beholding that notable worke of thy fingers called <hi rend="roman">Beautie,</hi> haue giuen glory to thy power &amp; wiſedome, that couldſt ſet ſuch amiableneſſe, and ſwéet fauour in a face not a foote compaſſe, the ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is but duſt: but I (ſuch was my corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) haue burnt in luſt at the ſight of it, and Sathan hath made it a ſtale, and a ſnare to intangle my ſoule, which now would faine flicker thence, and flie it to heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> I ſhould haue béene good to the poore, and néedy, remembring that Not to giue them, is to ſteale from them: but I (vile catiue) haue ſerued Mammon the God of Kuſt, the <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 15.</note> God of Moaths, the God of Théeues. Many a time hath Chriſt Ieſus (in his members) ſtood cold, and naked, &amp; hungry at my dore, and colde, and naked, and hungrie, haue I
<pb facs="tcp:13612:6"/> ſent him away. Yet would I not ſticke to ſpend hundreds vpon <hi rend="roman">Luxury,</hi> that infernall fire, whoſe matter is Gluttony, whoſe flame Arroganty, whoſe aſhes Obſcenitie. whoſe end eternall miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> I ſhould haue ſuccoured the name of my neighbour, and reioyced at his credit, and good eſtimation: I ſhould haue abhored all falſhood, and leaſins, &amp; ſpoken the truth from my hart: but I (vile wretch vnworthy to breath) could either neuer finde in hart to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe one good word on my brother, or very coldly commend him, though the graces of God ſhined in him extraordinarily. Oh what gladſome tioings was it to me when I hard of a profeſſor that was ouer taken with ſinne, I would be ſure to point at him as he went by, and cry there, there. And truely I made but a ieſt of a lye told in ieſt, as for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious lies, I reckoned them amongſt my good workes, and now and then I would broache a pernicions lye, and thinke little worſe of my ſelfe when I had done, for I was a right <hi rend="roman">Gretian.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> I ſhould haue borne a pure heart to my neighbour, and haue hampered, &amp; tamed the curſed rebellion of the fleſh: but I (no better than a lumpe of ſinne) haue wiſht that ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:13612:7"/> an houſe, and ſuch a cloſe of my neighbours were mine, and I euer thought the Corne on his land was better bladed, and fairer ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red than mine owne. To conclude: many an vncleane thought, laide by that Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice mine inbred concupiſence haue I hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp, when my conſcience aduiſd me to kill it in the ſhell.</p>
            <p>Thus I, the diſtreſſedſt wight vpon the face of the earth, haue broken all thy holy precepts, euen from the firſt vnto the laſt, from the greateſt vnto the leaſt. And now, O Lord, whether ſhall I flie for ſuccour? To thée? Woe is me, I dare not looke vp to heauen. To Angels? They gréeue, and bluſh at my rebellion. To men? alas they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rould in the ſame thraldome of ſinne with me. What then? ſhall I finally diſpaire with <hi rend="roman">Caine,</hi> and make away my ſelfe with <hi rend="roman">Iudas?</hi> No Lord, though thou kill me, yet ſtill will I put my truſt in thee. Doeſt thou ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme me with the tirrible waues of thy iudgements? Still wil I crie vnto thée euen out of the déepe, with <hi rend="roman">Dauid,</hi> and out of the <note place="margin">Pſal. 130. 1 Ionah. 2. 2.</note> belly of hell with <hi rend="roman">Ionah.</hi> Yea, bleſſed Ieſu, though thou ſhouldſt ſincke me, and drowne me, yet ſtill would I catch hould on thy cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and be taken vp dead with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie faſt claſpt in my hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:7"/>
            <p>In this ſort, poore ſinner, mourne, &amp; droope for the multitude of thine iniquities, not for a day or two, while the wound preſents it ſelfe freſh, and gréene before the eyes of thy minde, but continually, euen ſo long as thou féeleſt the enemy preſt to giue the onſet. Howbeit when the bridegrome Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is taken from thée (and peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is away) then, then is the fitteſt time <note place="margin">Math. 9. 15.</note> for ſadneſſe aboue all other.</p>
            <p>Now that thy ſoule may be cut, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the quick, I beſéech thée by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, that thou ponder theſe Motiues that enſue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Know firſt that the ſubſtance and quality of thine eye is a forcible argument to driue thée to wéeping. The Almighty hath made it of a liquid, fatty, and watriſh kinde of matter, ſo that it ſéemeth to delight in moiſture, as being a ſirrup to preſerue it in. Moreouer there are ſited aboue and vnder the eye, two wet &amp; ſpongious kernels, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to caſt a dew vpon it, and to make way for teares. Nay that the obſtinate and obdurate ſinner may be conuinced and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, if he ſweat not ſome teares for his offences, the Lord hath enuironed the Apple <note place="margin">Columb. lib. 10.</note> of the eye with a party coloured circle cald a <hi rend="roman">Raine-bow.</hi> Now it is not a ſhame for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:13612:8"/> to haue a <hi rend="roman">Raine-bow</hi> in his eye, &amp; yet neuer drizzle one teare for his ſinnes? Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian carry not about thée ſo tough, ſo braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſo ſtéeled an hart: good Chriſtian ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not about thée a paire of ſuch parched &amp; irrelenting eyes. Conſider what I ſay, &amp; the Lord giue thée vnderſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Regarde in the ſecond place, the vnruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thine eyes, and let that induce thée to be liberall in wéeping. God indéede ſet them in thine head (the tower of thy body) as Eſpials, and Scoutwatches, to diſeris danger a farre of: but ſuch is the diſorder of thy bad nature, that they will too ſoone put both thy body and ſoule in icopardy. Yet a little while, and thoſe two of thine that looke out by the windowes, will play the vag a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and intice thée to folly. For what art thou to <hi rend="roman">Dauid?</hi> And yet thoſe very eyes of <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> that lay ſoaked in teares at the time of his baniſhment, became afterwards trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, letting luſt into his boſome, when they darted from his roofe vpon <hi rend="roman">Bath-ſheba,</hi> and were the occaſion that he committed two haynous ſinnes dyed ſo déepely in crimſon, that time hath not yet worne out colour. If thou thinke thou canſt bleſſe thée from the euill to come, &amp; make a couenant with thine eyes as <hi rend="roman">Iob</hi> did, yet let thy heart be griped, <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 1.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:13612:8"/> and twinged, in regarde they haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore béene rowling and extrauagant eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, haue reſpect to the deſcription of ſinne. <hi rend="roman">Sinne is the tranſgreſſion of the Law.</hi> Wherein obſerue firſt what this lawe is which thou breakeſt. Secondly who this God is whom thou offendeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt then let it damp thée, &amp; diſquiet thy ſoule to conſider, that in euery looſe thought by thée conceiued, and in euery vnſauory word by thée vttered and in euery lewd déed by thée committed, thou haſt violated Gods law: which law is farre more excellent than the beautifull frame of the whole worlde, though in each part it be good, and in all the parts together excéeding good. For (ſuch is our purblindneſſe, that) the great booke of Nature is not able of it ſelfe to direct vs to the true God, as much reſembling that <hi rend="roman">A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian</hi> Aulter, wherein was written <hi rend="roman">Vnto the vnknowne God</hi> (but the lawe written <note place="margin">Acts. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23.</note> pointeth as iuſt to God as the finger to the dyall, and which commends it moſt of all) <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 7.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">conuerteth the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Go to now, miſerable, &amp; wretched ſinner, canſt thou by thy diſſolute life, cracke, and diſeſtéeme of this matchleſſe Iewell, and when when thou haſt done wilt thou not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſad, and ſober conſideration, opening
<pb facs="tcp:13612:9"/> the ſluces of thine eyes, and ſending forth a ſwift current of teares? Would not that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon be hangd in chaines who hauing broken moſt notoriouſlie the wholſome lawes of his Prince, takes no thought at all, but reuiles and playes at Tables all the while he is in priſon, with his héeles in yrons, and his neck in ſuſpence? Yes verily. Wel then take héed. For if after thou haſt lift vp thy horne moſt inſolently and puſht downe the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtatutes of the Lord, thou be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thy ſelfe, and confounded in thy ſelfe, but doeſt feaſt when thou ſhouldſt faſt, ſing when thou ſhouldſt ſobbe, laugh when thou ſhouldſt wéepe, thou art as néere in quality to the aforeſaid théefe, as can be well imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and therfore likely to come to ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, and fearefull end.</p>
            <p>Secondly, take knowledge who he is that enacted this law which thou haſt tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo ſhameleſly. It is no earthly Prince, nor Potentate, (a creature finite, ready to huffe out life at euery moment) but it is <hi rend="roman">Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 40. 12.</note> that mighty God, who ſpannes the heauen, and meaſures the waters in his fiſt, in reſpect of whom all nations are but as the drop of a bucket, nay nothing, nay leſſe <note place="margin">Nah. 1. 2.</note> than nothing, euen vanity. The God of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who hath his way in the whirlewinde,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:9"/> and in the ſtorme, at whoſe ſight the earth is burnt, the mountaines quake, the hils melt, the deuils ſhudder. O my déere brother, how can thy hart be light, ſith thou haſt offended ſo great a Maieſty? Why doeſt thou not put ſack-cloath about thy loynes, and an halter <note place="margin">Kings. 1. 20. 31.</note> about thy neck (with the ſeruants of <hi rend="roman">Benha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad)</hi> and crye out, Mercie good Lord, good Lord graunt mercy, for we haue heard that the King of <hi rend="roman">Iſraell</hi> is a mercifull King.</p>
            <p>If thou hadſt committed but petit treaſon againſt an earthly Prince, I perſwade me, it thou mightſt be admitted to his preſence thou wouldſt ſtoope, and looke forlornly with a paliſh chéeke, and vnkeambd beard, &amp; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected apparell, vſing theſe mutes as vocall ſpokeſmen, and interceſſors for thy pardon, and all becauſe, <hi rend="roman">The feare of the King is like <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 2</note> the roaring of a Lion.</hi> And is thy hart ſo cruſted, and rough caſt, that thou wilt not throw thy ſelfe euen below the earth, for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing that glorious and fearefull name <hi rend="roman">The Lord thy God?</hi> Shall a Graſſe-hopper <note place="margin">Deu. 28. 58</note> out-face the omnipotent, Clay the Potter, filth Puritie, Darkeneſſe Light, A wiſpe of ſtubble a conſuming fire, a ſinner of ſinners the holyeſt of all holyes?</p>
            <p>Surely if theſe perſwaſions make no dint, nor impreſſion, thy hart is harder than the
<pb facs="tcp:13612:10"/> Smiths Anuile: yet hearken ſtill (I beſéech thée) to the nature of this God, who chiefly ioyes in getting him honor by his boundles mercie. If this make thée not bewéepe thy perſonall ſinnes, thou haſt not ſo much as a ſparkle of grace truly working in thée.</p>
            <p>Wilt thou not be gréeued for offending thy God, who loued thée before thou waſt <note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 4.</note> borne, yea before the firſt ſtone of the worlds foundation was laide, who was thy hope, when thou hungeſt vpon thy mothers breſt, who guarded thée with Angels as thou lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſpralling in thy Cradle, and hath euer ſince fed thée, cloathed thée, preſerued thée? Didſt thou deſerue the leaſt of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings? If thou ſay thou didſt, thou art a lyer, and there is no truth in thée. For I ſay vnto thée, that he might haue made thée a Dog, or a toade, or a Serpent, &amp; haue done thée no wrong at all. Euen when thou waſt a delightfull burden to thy mother, taking thy paſtime in her wembe, and hauing no other mouth but thy nauell, then, euen then waſt thou odious to God (in thine owne nature) becauſe conceiued in ſin. Neither muſt thou thinke this to be rigor, for thy ſelfe canſt not abide a yong Woolfe, for that he hath in him the ſpawne and cruelty, and will deſtroy the flock when he comes to full growth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:10"/>
            <p>Why wilt thou recompence the Lord euill for good, and not rather pine away like the Hart that findeth no paſture for diſpleaſing ſo indulgent &amp; louing a father, whoſe kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſtretched out ſtill? Behold this God hanging for thy ſake vpon the croſſe: loe how he ſtretches out his arines to imbrace thée: loe how he bowes downe his head to kiſſe thée, loe how his hart is opened with a ſpeare to loue thée, to loue thée an vndutifull and graceleſſe child, vnworthy indéede to be called his childe. And yet he giues not period <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 12.</note> to his goodneſſe, but layes thée nearer his heart, marrying thée vnto him, and calling thée Chriſt by his owne name, to manifeſt the wonderfull (yet reall) coniunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and thée.</p>
            <p>O the depth of the riches of the mercy of this God, who hath hereto adioined another ſinguler benefit. What is that? He hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>créed that thou ſhouldeſt be borne (not a Turke, or a Jew, but) Engliſh, &amp; then there (not when <hi rend="roman">Pharaoh</hi> of hell and Antichriſt his vicegerent, made all true <hi rend="roman">Iſraelites</hi> weary of their liues with all manner of ſpirituall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which they laid vpon them moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but) when he ſet the Diadem on the head of that virgin Quéene, who hath giuen vs already thrée and fortye yeares of <hi rend="roman">Iubilee,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13612:11"/> wherein we ſit peaceably vnder our vines, &amp; go ioyfully to the Church to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golden bell of <hi rend="roman">Aaron</hi> ring ſweetely in the Pulpit, &amp; to feele the fragrant ſmell of his Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats. Be glad, yée heauens, at this, &amp; let the Rauens of the vallie picke out his eyes that curſeth this ancient mother in <hi rend="roman">Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could make more ample rehearſall of Gods ſpeciall fauour to thée, beloued Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but the intended quantity of the booke will not ſuffer me. Wherfore read on be not weary of well doing, and for thy next taſke thinke vpon thrée principall Effects of ſinne, that ſo thy ſorrow may be aggrauated.</p>
            <p>Firſt aſcertaine thy ſelfe that ſo long as thou weltreſt in thy wickedneſſe without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe &amp; touch of conſcience, thou art a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23 Luk. 15. 15</note> &amp; a vaſſall to Sinne, whoſe wages is <hi rend="roman">Death.</hi> A prodigall childe thou art. ſtrayed from thy good father into a farre countrey, where being all ragd, and tottered, &amp; eaten into the fleſh with vermine, thou art glad to become the deuils ſwinheard. Which tyrant hath taken thée priſoner to do his wil. &amp; mued <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2 26</note> thée vp in a far more noyſome dungeon than that wherein poore <hi rend="roman">Ieremie</hi> ſtacke ſo faſt.</p>
            <p>This is thy ſtate O man. Why then doeſt thou not thruſt forth teares, and ſmoake out ſighes, &amp; euen breake the kall of thine heart
<pb facs="tcp:13612:11"/> with ſorrow? Is ſwéet liberty ſo yrkeſome, &amp; yrkeſome bondage ſo ſwéet? Inquire of the Foules of the ayre, &amp; they will tell thée that fréedome in the wood is better than priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a cage of gold. Inquire of the Lions and they wil make anſwer that they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſéeke their meate at God in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, than haue it put into their mouths through the grate. Inquire of the Riuers &amp; they will reſolue thee that they would much ſooner lye open to winde &amp; weather at home in the ſea, than crawle neuer neuer ſo calmely by the gréeneſt and beſt ſented medowes. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée therefore by the mercies of God that thou bewayle thy miſerable vaſſallage. The <hi rend="roman">Babilonians</hi> of hell (the Deuil &amp; his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) haue led thée away captiue, &amp; the cruell <hi rend="roman">Edomits</hi> (thy ſinnes) prouoake them againſt thée, and both of them, by way of mockage, require a ſong &amp; melody of thée: then ſit thou downe vpon the waters bank, wéeping, and hanging thy harpe vpon the Willowes, for mirth at ſuch time is out of ſeaſon. Caſt not thy ſelfe vpon thy Iuory bed, eate not glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonouſly, drinke not Wine in boules, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy ſoule, thine afflicted <hi rend="roman">Ioſeph,</hi> who all this while hath his féet in hel ſtocks. The bleſſed father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt bore thine cares that thou maiſt heare and
<pb facs="tcp:13612:12"/> ſuffer theſe wordes of exhortation, and plow vp thy hart by his holy ſpirit, for it is made of a tough, and churliſh kinde of clay.</p>
            <p>I procéede to another Suaſiue. During the time of thine impenitencie, all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world band themſelues againſt thée, &amp; conſpire thine ouerthrow. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is for that the Lord of Hoſtes is march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward, whoſe faithfull &amp; ſworne ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers they be. Is not here ſufficient matter to cloud, &amp; ouercaſt thine eies, and to change thy ioy for mourning, thy beauty for aſhes, thy Oyle of gladnes for the ſpirit of heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? At dead time of night in thy ſoundeſt ſléepe, the Imbers on thine hearth deſire the winde (in their kinde) to leaue his naturall courſe of blowing aſſant, and to whip them vp, that ſo they may get matter to worke vpon. The ſpars, and rafters of thy houſe haue vowed to be ready to increaſe the flame at leſſe than an houres warning. Walkeſt thou in the ſtréet? The tiles threaten down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall. In the field? the ayre will conuay infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the earth will grone vnder thy ſoote as loath to beare ſo vnprofitable a burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nay what wilt thou ſay if the ſillieſt &amp; imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt creatures dog thée, and make thée wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy life? Are Frogs, and Lice, &amp; Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers nothing with thée? Doth not one
<pb facs="tcp:13612:12"/> poore Gnat (hartning on her ſelfe to battaile with her Cornet which ſhe winds ſo laſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) waken thée, and make thée ſtart with her feeble ſting? Then what would a legion of Gnats doe? Ah ſinfull ſoule, and laden with iniquity, is thy hart made of rubbiſh, &amp; thine eye of Marble, that the one will not giue againe, the other become dankiſh? Knoweſt thou not what it is to haue the ſtones of the field out of league with thée, and the beaſts of the field out of league with thée? Take an example of <hi rend="roman">Ionah,</hi> and ſée how he was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led when God muſtered vp ſuch forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in his diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>After this Prophet had long laboured, and toyled in <hi rend="roman">Iſraell,</hi> and could doe no good, the Lord gaue him expreſſe charge to remooue his plow into the <hi rend="roman">Nineuites</hi> fielde to ſhame her. He (vnmindfull of his commiſſion) paies the fare, and is ſhipt. For <hi rend="roman">Tharſhiſh</hi> he, he is reſolud. While he thus ſtrugled with diuine prouidence, the Winds (at their Creators commaund) brake looſe, &amp; bad the Mariners <note place="margin">Ionah. 1. 4.</note> deliuer <hi rend="roman">Ionah.</hi> The Sea ſawe that, and was wroth, and bad the Marriners deliuer <hi rend="roman">Ionah.</hi> The Whale laye watching all this while, and bad the Marriners deliuer <hi rend="roman">Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi> The ſhip (poore winged veſſell) laye ſwooning vpon the billowes, and bad the
<pb facs="tcp:13612:13"/> Marriners vnballaſe her of <hi rend="roman">Ionah.</hi> Nay <hi rend="roman">Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> ſtood vp againſt <hi rend="roman">Ionah,</hi> and beſought the Marriners to tumble him into the large Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of the ſea. How now mery ſinner, doth not the ſenere vſage of the man of God appall thée? If ſo righteous a man be thus harſhly intreated by the creatures, where wilt thou an vngodly and vnrepentant man appeare? O <hi rend="roman">Sampſon,</hi> why ſuffereſt thou lady Pleaſure to play the <hi rend="roman">Delilah,</hi> dandling thée on her knée, til ſhe haue ſhaued of all thy goodneſſe, &amp; made thée wretched, &amp; féeble, and impotent? what <hi rend="roman">Samplon, Sampſon,</hi> fend for thy ſelf, the <hi rend="roman">Philiſtnes</hi> are vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée <hi rend="roman">Sampſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remaineth a third effect of ſinne, ſufficient to ſplit thy hart, be thou not inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly blockiſh, wilfully nefarious, extreamly impious. It is this. All creatures in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world grone vnder the heauy burden of thy ſinnes yea the Creator himſelfe. S. <hi rend="roman">Paul</hi> affirmes this (in part) moſt excellently. <hi rend="roman">For we know</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 11.</note> (ſaith he) <hi rend="roman">that euery creature groaneth with vs alſo, and trauaileth in paine together vnto this preſent, becauſe it is ſubiect to vanitie, &amp; vnder the bondage of corruption.</hi> The world left being a world, when <hi rend="roman">Adam</hi> left béeing obedient, it was neuer beautifull, nor chéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſince it waxed old in youth through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ataxies and diſorders, and at this day
<pb facs="tcp:13612:13"/> lyes bed-rid, waiting with a ſeruent deſire for the glorious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>When <hi rend="roman">Iſraelits</hi> ſinnes were ripe, and calde for the ſickle, rotten, &amp; cryed for the coraſtue, what followde? The harmeleſſe creatures muſt pay for it. The beaſts of the field, and the foules of the heauen muſt be cut off, and <note place="margin">Hoſe. 4. 2. 3</note> the Fiſhes of the ſea muſt be taken away. The Prophet <hi rend="roman">Ieremie</hi> (bewailing the piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">Lam. 2. 4.</note> eſtate of <hi rend="roman">Ieruſalem)</hi> teſtifieth, that the very wayes of <hi rend="roman">Sion,</hi> and the rampart, &amp; wall did lament for the iniquitie of the Iewes. Sée, ſée, my beloued, how the dumbe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures complaine vnder the intollerable waight of thy ſinnes, while thou ietteſt vp and downe with a Cammels proud neck, &amp; beareſt no part in their ſong of ſorrow. Thy corne which thou hopedſt would growe plumpe in the eare, is blaſted in the prime, and it thanks thée for it. Thy cloſe is peſterd with thornes and thiſtles, and other curſed and vntimely fruite, and it thankes thée for it. Thy fiſhes are frozen to thy pond, &amp; they ſilently thanke thée for it. O what a rack, what a gybbet would this be to thy ſoule, if thou hadſt any grace? But thou (more ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe then ſenceleſneſſe) euen when fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie is offered to caſt duſt vpon thy head, and that thine eye, euen thine eye ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:13612:14"/> ſhoure forth teares day and night, goeſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily away, regardleſſe of ſo lamentable ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles. What is this but a cleare demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſo continuing thou art within an inch of hell? Water is an heauie ſubſtance, and yet if a man lay cloſe to the bottome of the ſea, he ſhould féele no waight, becauſe <hi rend="roman">No Element is heauy in it proper place.</hi> The whole world is cruſhed with the ponderouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy ſinnes, and thou féeleſt it not: A ſhrewd token that ſinne is where it would be. Alas for pitty, why wilt thou dye? why wilt thou ſtrangle thy ſoule with ſo full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution? If thou loue God, who loued thée firſt, be no longer an Heafer of thrée yeares olde (euer liuing in pleaſure, &amp; neuer féeling ſorrow) but let thy bowels ſound like an Harpe, or Shawme, for thy tranſgreſſions, and now at length ſigh out this exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Oh that mine head were full of water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might wéepe day and night for my manifold and bloody ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And that thy hart may yet waxe colder within thy body, know further that thy ſins lye ſo ſore vpon thy ſwéete Saniours back, that he can take no reſt. Hearke how he complaineth. Beholde I am preſſed vnder <note place="margin">Amo. 2. 13</note> thy ſinnes euen as a Cart is preſſed that is
<pb facs="tcp:13612:14"/> full of ſheaues. Pitie O pitie thy ſelfe, if not take pitie vpon thy Redéemer, who is preſt downe to hell with the heauy ſheaues of ſinne which thou haſt pickt vpon him moſt cruelly, more like a Iew than a Chriſtian. It was thou, O wretch, that didſt caſt him into his agony, where he ſwet ſuch a ſweat, that the drops of blood trickled downe apace, and the Angels were faine to comfort him. It was thou, O wretch, that betraiedſt him with a kiſſe, &amp; ſoldſt him for a little pleaſure of ſinne, not worth thirtie péeces of ſiluer. It was thou, O wretch, that cameſt vnto him with ſwords and ſtaues, as if he had béene a théefe, who indéede thought it no robbery to be equall with God. It was thou, O wretch that didſt whip him, and clap a crowne of thornes vpon his head, mocking him, &amp; ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his face. O cruelty? If thou haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpit, thou getteſt thée to the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or behinde the doore for manners ſake, and yet thou makeſt no bones of ſpitting in the face of the God of Angels. It was thou, O wretch, that didſt ſtrip him naked, &amp; riuet his hands and féet to the croſſe, flouting him euen when he indured for thy ſake the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wrath of God his Father.</p>
            <p>Behold thy Redcéemer, offering vp praiers with ſtrong crying, and teares, and art thou
<pb facs="tcp:13612:15"/> ſrolicking? The daughters of <hi rend="roman">Ieruſalem</hi> wéepe, the Virgin <hi rend="roman">Mary</hi> is pierced through with the ſword of ſorrow, and dooſt thou run ryot, and chop away thy ſoule for a mite of pleaſure? The Sunne lends night in midſt of day, the vaile of the Temple is rent from the top to the bottom, the earth quaketh, the <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 51.</note> ſtones cléeue, the graues open, and art thou fatting thy ſelfe with merriment? And mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thou for all this to ſaile to heauen by heauen? Can there be two heauens? If thou ſtill play the Epicure, letting theſe reaſons which the ſcripture yéeldeth ſo bounteouſly rebound from thine eye, eare, and hart, like a Tenniſe from the ground, I (euen plunged in a gulfe of ſorrow, to ſée thée like a frantick ſmile when y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dingeſt thy knuckles againſt what is next thée, till the blood ſpin out) muſt leaue thée to the ſecret councell of God, &amp; if thou néeds wilt periſh, thy blood will be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine owne ſoule. But I truſt theſe words ſhall prooue vnto thée the ſwéet ſauour of life vnto life, and not of death vnto death: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be dilligent in waighing two reaſons moe, ſo will I betake me to the remainder.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the bleſſedneſſe of this godly ſorrow. Doeſt thou moleſt the ayre with ſighes, and the earth with teares, not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſaite, and forced, but ſincere and penirent?
<pb facs="tcp:13612:15"/> Reioyce, and be glad. Thou art in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Grace, the forerunner of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Before the conuerſion, and <note place="margin">Zeph: 1. 12</note> new ſpirituall byrth, thou was frozen in the dregs of thy ſinne, &amp; there was ſuch a thicke Ice vpon thy ſoule, that the euill Angelles, ſhotte at pricks (as it were) and droue carts vpon it: but ſince the <hi rend="roman">Holy Ghoſt</hi> (which the <note place="margin">Math. 3. 12</note> Goſpell compared to fire) hath caught holde on thée, thy congealed nature is diſſolued, and thawed into a flood of teares.</p>
            <p>Wouldſt thou thinke it? There is not a <note place="margin">Pſal: 56. 8.</note> teare ſhed for ſinne, but God catches it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it falles to the ground, and treaſureth it vp in his bottle. Not a teare ſpent in this ſort, which thou ſhalt not finde vpon recorde in heauen, ſo ſoone as euer thy ſoule is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſde. In ſumme: the Lambe in the midſt of the Thorne, will (with his owne hand) wipe away al teares from thine eyes. Thus they that ſowe in teares, ſhall reape in ioye. Bleſſed art thou if thou now wéep, for thou <note place="margin">Reue. 7. 17</note> ſhalt laugh, bleſſed art thou if thou now mourne, for thou ſhalt be comforted. Yet a very little while, and he that ſhall come, <note place="margin">Luck. 6. 21</note> will come, and will not tary.</p>
            <p>The laſt Motiue is the conſideration of their deplored eſtate, who ayming at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the bodyes corrupt ſatiſfaction,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:16"/> bury the excellent deſignes of the ſoule in muddy ſenſuall pleaſure, terming ſorrow for ſinne nothing els but a ſullen paſſion be got betwéene Feare, and Melancholy, the ſilly effect of the fooliſhnes of Prenching. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſhall I liken this generation? They are like vnto the fat Kine of <hi rend="roman">Baſhan</hi> that are in the mountaine of <hi rend="roman">Samaria,</hi> appointed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaughter. They are like vnto Théeues that goe through a fayre ſloured field to the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. They are like vnto Riuers that run ſwéet, &amp; freſh into the ſalt ſea. They are like vnto Paſſengers laide along to ſléepe vnder ſhady trées, who wakning ſince themſelues ſwelted with the heate of the remooued ſun.</p>
            <p>Theſe Riotours that neuer came where true ſorrow grew, firſt are baſe. For them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues affirme that pleaſure is for the body, &amp; all men know the body is for the ſoule: ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come they ſeruants to their ſeruants ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Secondly their eſtate is damnable in life, in death, after death. In life, for their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are bereft of ſence and motion, by that gangrene ſinne, and throughly burnt with a ſearing Yron. If a man ſhould cut them vp he ſhould finde no hart in them, for <hi rend="roman">Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Wine, and new Wine, haue taken <note place="margin">Hoſe. 4. 11.</note> away their hart.</hi> This is a plague of all plagues. The ſtone in the bladder is a grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb facs="tcp:13612:16"/> diſeaſe, ſo is the ſtone in the backe, but there is no diſeaſe to the ſtone in the hart. Some read the Bible, and finding the wrath of God to ſmoake againſt ſinners in the olde Teſtament, ſomtime with ſtoning, ſomtime with the earth ſwallowing her inhabitants, ſomtime with fire &amp; brimſtone from heauen, they wonder why God is ſo gentle now a dayes as to let ſinne alone, which growes ſo ranke in all places. Alas it is true (wretches that we are) we are all of one language (quite contrary to the good language of <hi rend="roman">Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan)</hi> &amp; we build Towers of <hi rend="roman">Babel</hi> (Towres of ſinne and confuſion) whoſe pinacles ſpire vp to heauen, and cry out in the eares of the Lord, Thou God to whome vengeance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, thou God to whom vengeance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, ſhew thy ſelfe. And verily if we goe on as we doe, out-ſinning all the regions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs, and turning vnto our owne race as a horſe ruſheth into the battaile, we ſhall driue the Lord in his anger to exclaime, O, they haue put out my eyes, as the <hi rend="roman">Philiſtins</hi> did <hi rend="roman">Sampſons</hi> my type, they multiply abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as if I had no prouidence: lead me lead me to the maine pillers of the land, the poſts whereon the houſe ſtandeth, that ſo I may bring the realme vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heads, &amp; be at once auenged of them for my two eyes.
<pb facs="tcp:13612:17"/> But (to anſwer the queſtion) I auouch i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confidently that the Lorde doth plague the impenitent of this land more ſharply and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely now in theſe dayes of peace, then he did malefactors in former ages. And I prooue it thus. Then he puniſhed the body, now he puniſheth the ſoule, deliuering theſe men vp into a reprobate ſence, &amp; giuing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill liberty to eare-marke them. It is the fearefulleſt iudgment in the world, when ſin is puniſhed with ſinne, and this is the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe times. Wo, wo, wo vnto vs, for we are ſick of ſinne vnto death, and yet féele it not, nay like <hi rend="roman">Gadarens,</hi> we driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Lord of life the deare Phyſitian of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>If any man be deſirous to know the cauſe of ſo vniuerſall a deſertion, and embrawning of the hart, I muſt tell him that we are poore with riches, pale with beauty, ſicke with health, euill with good. Peace, and Plenty (the mother, and daughter) haue ſo led and pampred vs, that we are waxen wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and kick againſt the Lord, Search the Scripture who will, he ſhall euer finde that leanneſſe of ſoule hath béene ſent amongſt Quailes, &amp; that exceſſiue mirth, gluttony, and chambering, make men purſie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weildſome, and to God vnſeruiceable.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:17"/>
            <p>By this deare Chriſtian brother, mayeſt thou take a ſcantling of their wretched e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in this life who do nothing els but ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill their ſenſuall luſts and appetites. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly me thinkes this one iudgement that vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nlly befalleth Belly-gods on earth, ſhould make our Luſty blouds afraid. But (alas) they haue eyes, and ſee not, eares and heare not, harts and vnderſtand not.</p>
            <p>They drinke till they be drounde in fire, and ſhoote chaineſhot of roaring oathes that make the windowes of heauen to totter, (in my conſcience they made the earth quake ſo lately.) Tel them of it, they breake ieſts, and like the prophane <hi rend="roman">Iſralits,</hi> rebuke the Prieſt. <note place="margin">Hoſea. 4. 4.</note> Yet when they lye vpon their death beds, tumbling, and toſſing, and telling the clock: when the flaſhes of hell fire preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to their conſciences, and the bloody wounds appeare which they gaue their owne ſoules in the dayes of their iollitye: when that wilde beaſt Sin that hath ſo long ſlept at the dore of their harts, and ſtird not, is ſuddainely awaked, and flyes in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ready to pull out their throates: when ſwarmes of iniquities humme like flyes about them, and like Frogges ſcrall vpon them, and croke vengeance againſt them: then tell me if they deſcend not from the
<pb facs="tcp:13612:18"/> treble keyes of mirth to the graue keyes of ſorrow: tell me then if they tremble not like an Aſpine leafe, or like the hartleſſe Deare at the noyſe of the thunder-cracke. Then ſend for <hi rend="roman">Moſes,</hi> ſend for the Preacher, then good people pray for me, O whither ſhall I flie from the Arrowes of the Almightie, that part my ribbes, and wound me incurably: Alas I thought I could haue repented at the laſt gaſpe, euen when I was fetching my ſoule ſighes, but now I finde to my paine, that repentance is the guift of God. O that I might dye the death of the righteous. This will be the out-crye of euery one of them, dye not their harts like ſtones within <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25. 37.</note> them, as <hi rend="roman">Nabals</hi> did.</p>
            <p>But when the date of their life is out, and their ſoules vnbodied, then is that truely brought to paſſe which our Sauiour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, Woe bée to you that now laugh, <note place="margin">Luk. 6. 25.</note> for yée ſhall wéepe, and waile. When they once put their heades within hell gates, and heare the feareful yelling of damned ſpirits, that féele no comfort, no releaſe, no eaſe, nor any thing but amaze and horror, then will they wiſh, &amp; wiſh that they had wept their eies out, &amp; ſighed their lungs in péeces, but it will be too late. Then will each of them crye out, Curſed be the day wherin I was borne,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:18"/> curſed be the paps that gaue me ſuck, curſed be the knées that preuented me, for damned I was, damned I am, damned I ſhall be for euer more. O whether (poore forſaken) ſhall I go from diſtreſſe, ſince no remooue can leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen my ſorrowes, &amp; euery place preſents like face of miſery? Alas what comfort ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue when the God of all comfort is away? Alas it is a long night that's neuer day, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull fire that's neuer quenched, a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful torment that hath neuer end, but laſteth for a time, &amp; times, &amp; no time, euen for euer. O hell, hell, thy fire is intollerable hot, (yet without any light to giue a ſoule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort) the <hi rend="roman">breath of the Lord like a Riuer of Brimſtone doth kindle it.</hi> O that ſome mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine would <note place="margin">Iſai. 30. 33.</note> fall on me, &amp; hide me from the preſence of the Lambe, whom if I had kiſt, he had not béene angry, and I had neuer come to this. O that I had béene borne a Katte, or a Spider, or a Load, for ſo ſhould my ſoule haue vaniſhed to nothing, whereas now it is ſubſtantiue, alwayes dying, yet neuer dead. Worme of conſcience, when, oh when wilt thou dye? wilt thou neuer leaue tugging and tearing my ſoule? Father <hi rend="roman">Abraham,</hi> one drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to coole my tongue, good father <hi rend="roman">Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, why go I about to blazon the armes of hell, ſince they paſſe the power of any
<pb facs="tcp:13612:19"/> pencils expreſſing, or mindes imagination? Suppoſe a man laid his limmes on a choice fetherbed, hauing before him all ſightly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects for the eye, and all toothſome meates for the taſte, and the ſwéeteſt accorde in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick for the eare, and were bound to remaine ſo without ſtirring a ioynt but for twenty yeares: Oh how often would he looke vp to heauen pittifully, and long for death as for a treaſure, rather than indure ſo ſoft a pnniſhment? What then will become of that vnhappy ſoule, who hauing ſported out his life muſt be hurried by Deuils into hell, where his bed ſhall be a red-hot gridyron, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of damned ghoſts his beſt ſightes, his dyet Diſpayre, his Muſicke Gnaſhing of Téeth, aſſiſted with dreadfull ſhriekes, and Clamorous lamentations, not for twenty or forty yéeres, but for as many thouſands of yeares as there be drops in the Sea, and Sands on the ſhore, and then to begin freſh againe euerlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Theſe motiues well reſpected, and not ouerly ſuruaide, what flintie hart will not riue, and what ſinfull ſoule will not houle after the maner of Dragons? My moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; moſt déere Chriſtian brother, let me become not a ſuter, but a beggar vnto thée: <hi rend="roman">For Ieſus Chriſts ſake I aske it,</hi> humble thy
<pb facs="tcp:13612:19"/> ſelfe with faſting, wéeping and mourning: humble thy ſelfe with faſting, wéeping, and mourning, <hi rend="roman">For Ieſus Chriſtes ſake I aske it.</hi> If the nature of thine eye cannot mooue thée, then let the excellencie of Gods lawe which thou haſt broken, perſwade thée. If the excellencie of Gods law which thou haſt broken cannot perſwade thée, let the mighty Maieſty of the Lord rouze thée. If the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Maieſty of the Lorde cannot rouze thée, let the mercifulneſſe of the ſame God allure thée. If the mercifulneſſe of God cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure thée, let the peſtilent effects of ſinne curbe thée If the peſtilent effects of ſinne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not curbe thée, then let the inſupportable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell kill thée dead, and rent thée in péeces.</p>
            <p>As for thée, O young man, reioyce in thy <note place="margin">Eccle. 10. 9</note> youth, &amp; let thine hart chéere thée in the daies of thy youth, &amp; walke in the wayes of thine hart, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of thine eies, but know that for al this God wil bring thée to iudgement.</p>
            <p>Brutiſh Epicure, that poſteſt to the Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe at the ſound of the Trumpet, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt money to behold their vanities, who ſet vp the Flag of defiance to vertue, but wilt in no wiſe bee brought to the Church to mourne though the Preacher lift vp his voyce like a trumpet, &amp; cry alowd, <hi rend="roman">Ho, come,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:20"/> and buy Wine and Milke without ſiluer:</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <note place="margin">Iſaia. 55. 1.</note> in thy merriment, doe: but know that for all this God will bring thée to iudgement.</p>
            <p>Théeuiſh adulterer, that feloniouſly takeſt away thy poore neighbours little ſhéepe, that eates of his owne morſels, drinkes of his owne cup, &amp; ſléepes in his boſome: laugh on, ſweare on, whore on: but know that for all this God will bring thée to iudgement.</p>
            <p>To returne to thée (brother mine) whoſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation I deſire in my hart: thoſe Inſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; Induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which the Lord hath put into my minde, haue I imparted to thee: And yet I finde not my ſelfe ſatiſfied, till I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thée with certaine rubbes which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than will caſt in thy way, to ſtop thée from running ſmoothly to this godly ſorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt Impediment is the want of the word preached. For how canſt thou mourne, if <hi rend="roman">Iohn Baptiſt</hi> mourne not to thée, or cal thy place <hi rend="roman">Bochim</hi> (that is by interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) <hi rend="roman">Wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iud. 2. 4. 5.</note> vnleſſe <hi rend="roman">Phineas,</hi> or ſome zelous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet forbeare Incarnatiue ſalues, and giue thée coraſiues, rebuke thée ſharpely, and ſounding thy ſinnes to the bottome? <hi rend="roman">Peter</hi> muſt not bawke thy wickedneſſe, but taxe <note place="margin">Acts. 2. 36.</note> thée roundly, and point out <hi rend="roman">Ieſus</hi> whome thou haſt crucified, elſe wilt thou not be prickt in thy heart, nor demaund what thou
<pb facs="tcp:13612:20"/> ſhalt do to be ſaued. O then, my brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, and longed for, my ioy &amp; my crowne (I hope) as euer thou meaneſt to haue a grudging in thy conſcience for thy many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde corruptions, be a diligent frequenter of powerfull Sermons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Hindrance, is the hope of long life. Soule (ſaith the ritch man) take thine <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 19</note> eaſe. Why ſo? Thou haſt much goods laide vppe for many yeares. Take héede, take héede of this faulte, for it is inbred. The Adulterer will graunt that Adulterye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generall, is naught: but when he deſcends to this, or that ſpeciall Adultrye, then hée varniſheth it ouer with ſome vayne ſhewe of reaſon and approueth it. Right ſo thou wilt confeſſe by wordes of courſe (eſpecially when thou art crauing a bond for ſecurity) that man is mortal, man is mortal: but when it comes to this, that thou, thou in particular, muſt ſhortly bée borne on foure mens ſhoulders to the place of deade mens ſculs, then thou ſootheſt thy ſelfe, &amp; art fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incredulous, as if thy life were thine owne fée-ſimple. Harke in thine eare. Thou art a Dyue-dapper, péering vp, and downe agayne in a moment, thou cameſt by the wombe, and muſt goe by the graue. Harke in thine eare. Thou dwelleſt in an houſe <note place="margin">Iob. 4. 19</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:13612:21"/> of clay, in a tent, pitcht to day, remooued to morrow, and Corruption is thy father, the worme thy mother, and thy ſiſter, Where is <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 1</note> louely <hi rend="roman">Abſolon?</hi> Where is ſtrong <hi rend="roman">Og,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſtreake himſelfe on his bed of yron? Dead. All, all goe naked out of the world, thou boughteſt life, and muſt pay for it with death. Aſſure thy ſelfe, whoſoeuer readeſt this booke, that ere many yeares, or decades of months be paſt, Death (mounted on his <note place="margin">Reuel. 6. 8.</note> pale horſe) will rap at thy doore, and alight, &amp; carry thée away (bound head and foote) to a land darke as darkneſſe it ſelfe. What then remaineth, but that thou preſently make <note place="margin">Ioh. 19. 41</note> thy graue with <hi rend="roman">Ioſeph</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Arimathea</hi> in thy Garden (the place of thy delight) mourning each daye amidſt thy moſt tickling plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as if the Sunne of thy life were ſure to ſet at night? When ſhall I pray for thée, ſaith <hi rend="roman">Moſes</hi> to <hi rend="roman">Pharaoh?</hi> To morrowe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers <note place="margin">Exod. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">Pharaoh.</hi> He ſhould haue ſaid <hi rend="roman">To day.</hi> Be not a kinne to <hi rend="roman">Pharaoh.</hi> For if thou play the ignamous and ſloathfull ſeruant, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to eate, and drinke with the drunken, <note place="margin">Math. 24. 49. 50.</note> thy Maiſter Chriſt will come in a day when thou lookeſt not for him, and in an houre that thou art not aware of, and will cut thée off, and giue thée thy portion with hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, there ſhall be wéeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:13612:21"/> of téeth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third let is Companie, eſpecially me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Company. Therefore the Prophet <hi rend="roman">Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 4.</note> would haue vs examine our ſelues (qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly) on our Beds. It is ſtoryed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts that <hi rend="roman">Peter went out</hi> (from the <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 62</note> concourſe of people in the high Prieſts hall) <hi rend="roman">and then he wept bitterly. It is better to goe to the houſe of mourning than of feaſting,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 4.</note> ſaith <hi rend="roman">Salomon.</hi> The king of glorye ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſo dignifieth the Gentleman, that he knockes at his hart by his holy ſpirit, and bids him open the doore that he may enter in. Héere begins he to ſighe at the view of his ſinnes. Preſently comes me in a Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an (whom God ſends to prooue him, whom the Deuill ſends to ſpoile him) and he with a payre of Cardes, and a Cup of neate Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, thruſts Ieſus out into the Stable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no roome for him in the Inne. Thus be the good motions of the holye Ghoſte extinguiſhed by the acceſſe of a Gameſter, that Schooles his young mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Arte of <hi rend="roman">Driuing away time.</hi> Driue away time? Is Tyme ſo ſlow-footed that it néedes driuing? My friend: if a ſinner intice thée to ſport when the Feuer of thy ſinnes begins to ſhake thée, conſent not to him, Rather goe aſide (as a man throwne
<pb facs="tcp:13612:22"/> from the world) and then let thy belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let thy lips ſhake, let rottenueſſe enter into thy bones. Learne of the Nightingale who when ſhe is robd of her yonglings, gets her to ſome ſolitarie trée, where ſhe bewailes her vnhappie marriage. Abſtract, and ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thy ſelfe, flée reſorte, ſay vnto laughter thou art madde, haunt vntrodden pathes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Lillies of the fielde to cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in blacke, and accompanie thée in thy dolefull paſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth Impediment is Impayring of health. <hi rend="roman">A ioyfull hart</hi> (ſaith the <hi rend="roman">Wiſeman) cauſeth good health, but a ſorrowfull minde <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 22</note> dryeth vp the bones.</hi> Let not this diſmay thée, better go ſickly to heauen, than health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to hell. Be not all for thy bodie, nothing for thy ſoule, but like the Lapidarie, eſtéeme the Iewell farre aboue the rinde or barke: Moreouer I affirme that it is the care of this worlde that brings a Calender into the bones, and ſnowes vpon mens heades ſo timely, and not this ſorrow which we mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie. For as the Sea at high water, if an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred with a boyſtrous wind, threatneth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deluge to the earth, and yet ſuddainely it giues backe, and runnes away like a cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard: ſo the panges, and gréeuances of the righteous, ſtird vp by the iuſtice of God,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:22"/> euen when they ſéeme to deuoure, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of his mercy. They are as ſorrowing and yet alwayes reioycing by reaſon of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comfort which putteth life into them. Heauines may indure for a night, but ioye wilbe ſure to be with them in the morning.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt and worſt Let, is the holding the mortality of the ſoule. There is a curſed ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that ſit downe to eate, and drinke, and riſe vp to play, and hold that their ſoules in death vaniſh away like a dogges. This Satanicall paradoxe poſſeſt the hart of that great Phiſition <hi rend="roman">Galen.</hi> A man might haue caſt his water and found filthy ſediments of Athiſme. But he is dead long ago, &amp; I would this ſin had died with him. Good Chriſtian, neuer come thou nere thoſe Carrions that maintaine the ſoule to be a vapour, vnleſſe thou haue the winde of them. That thou maiſt be aſſured of the ſoules immortality, harken to theſe pregnant, and vnanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proofes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Our fathers are the fathers of our bodyes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 9. Eccle. 12. 7.</note> (not of our ſoules) <hi rend="roman">ſaith the Apoſtle. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite returnes to God that gaue it,</hi> ſaith the Preacher. <hi rend="roman">The Lord breathed the ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note> mans body,</hi> ſaith <hi rend="roman">Moſes:</hi> Therefore is it not elementary, therefore is it euerlaſting. But becauſe the diſputer of this worlde
<pb facs="tcp:13612:23"/> renounces Chriſtian principles, we will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the liſtes of reaſon with him (a little) and foile him in his proper element. The ſence is ſo corrupted by a great obiect, that it cannot indure the leſſe. For example. The eye is ſo dazeled with the beames of the Sun, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not iudicially diſcerne colours in an obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer light. It is contrary with the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. For the more vehement the obiect is whereabout it is conuerſant, the more forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is it in comprehending the inferiour. An euident demonſtration of the ſoules diuinity I omit the horror of conſcience, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not poſſibly light vpon the body (it being a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall puniſhment) nor yet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule, were it not a ſubſiſting eſſence. And I will but tutch the moſt admirable gradation of the creatures, ſome whereof are onely bodily, as beaſts: ſome ſpirituall as Angels: ſome both ſpirituall, and ſenſible, as man: the one in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his ſoule, the other of his body. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my beloued, be thou ſtedfaſt, immoouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; aboundant in mourning for thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, for as much as thou knoweſt thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord.</p>
            <p>If thou finde thy ſoule at od times vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to thinke of flitting, impute that to her illneſſe: for naturally ſhe is eſtranged from the father of lights, and lodging ſo warmely
<pb facs="tcp:13612:23"/> and peaceably in the body, ſhe is not ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to remooue as ſhe ought. The Infant is at harts-caſe in the mothers wombe, and would not change it for a pallace: yet when it is borne, and comes to diſcretion, it cannot indure to thinke of the cloſet where it lay en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped. The ſoule delighteth now to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the body, but when death hath brought it to a ioyfull birth after a long trauaile, O then it would not be impriſon'd againe in the body for a thouſand worlds. And thus by Gods goodneſſe haue I gone through the Impediments.</p>
            <p>And now, good brother, that I haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thée a potion, the vertue whereof I truſt hath had full courſe to runne throughout all thy vaynes: I am for a farewell to leaue thée a ſwéete Electuary, or Iulep for thy comfort. It is a Moderation in ſorrowing. For the tempter will couet to beſnare thy ſoule with intollerable anguiſhe, that ſo (with <hi rend="roman">Cain)</hi> thou maieſt complaine that thy ſinnes are greater than can be forgiuen. O pray, pray, pray for patience, and comfort of the holy Ghoſt, for a wounded ſpirite who can beare? <hi rend="roman">Iob,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> (a bleſſed pare of Saints) mourned like Doues, and Pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, when the Lord cauſed them to poſſeſſe <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 14.</note> the ſinnes of their youth, Surely no wiſdom
<pb facs="tcp:13612:24"/> can counſell, no counſel can aduiſe, no aduiſe can aſſwage a perplexed conſcience, nor any thing els, but onely the hart bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, which blood hee hath powred out ſo plenteouſly for all true penitent ſinners that they may bath themſelues therein. Then cry inceſſantly, and importunately, O ſonne of <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> haue mercy on me, open mine eyes, heale my woundes, cure my Maladies, euen for thy goodnes ſake, O Lord. Remember the heauenly wordes Chriſt vttered in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame agony of his ſoule; My God, my God why haſt thou forſaken me? Behold how hée calleth his father his God twice, what time his wrath ceazed vpon him in an incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible maner. Sorrow not too much when the Lord openeth the booke of thy conſcience (all blurd, and blotted with ſinne) but bee of good cheare, &amp; kiſſe his holy hand euen when he ſtriketh thée. The father of mercies, and God of al conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be thy Caſtle of defence in all thy tribulations, &amp; ſpirituall conflicts, that thou maiſt be able to comfort others in the like diſtreſſe by the ſame comfort wherewith thou thy ſelfe art com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted of him. Amen.</p>
            <trailer rend="roman">FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:24"/>
            <head>A Morning praier to bev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in priuate families.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord our God and heauenly Father, wee thy vnworthie children doe here come into thy moſt holy and heauenly preſence to giue thée praiſe &amp; glory, for al thy great mercies and manifold bleſſings towards vs: eſpecially for that thou haſt preſerued vs this night paſt, from all the dangers and feares thereof, haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs quiet reſt to our bodies, and brought vs now ſafely to the beginning of this day, and doeſt now a freſh renew all thy mercies vpon vs as the Eagle reneweth her bill, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs all things aboundantly to enioy: as food, raiment, health, peace, libertie, and frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many miſeries, diſeaſes, caſualties, and calamities which wée are ſubiect vnto in this life euery minute of an houre: and not only ſo, but alſo for vouchſafing vnto vs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things, not onely for neceſſitie, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for delight alſo. But aboue all (deare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) we praiſe thy name for the bleſſings of a better life, ſpecially for thy moſt holy word and ſacraments, and all the good wée enioy thereby: for the continuance of the Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:13612:25"/> amongſt vs: for the death of thy ſonne &amp; all that happineſſe which we haue thereby. Alſo becauſe thou haſt choſen vs to life before we were, and that of thy méere goodneſſe, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued fauour towards vs, and haſt called vs in thine appointed time, iuſtified by thy grace, ſanctified vs by thy ſpirit, &amp; adopted vs to be thine owne children, &amp; heires apparant to the great crowne. O Lord open our eyes euery day more &amp; more to ſée and conſider of thy great and maruailous loue to vs in all theſe things: that by the due conſideration therof, our harts may be drawne yet nearer vnto thée, euen more to loue thée, feare thée, and obey thée: that as thou art enlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs in mercie, ſo we may be enlarged towards thée in thankſgiuing: and as thou doſt abound towards vs in goodneſſe, ſo we may abound towards thée in obedience and loue. And ſith (deare father) thou art neuer wearie of doing vs good, not withſtanding all our vnworthineſſe &amp; naughtineſſe, therefore let the conſideration of thy great mercy and fatherly kindneſſe towardes vs, euen as it were force our hearts, &amp; compell vs to come into thy moſt glorious preſence with new ſongs of thankſgiuing in our mouths. Wée pray thée (O moſt mercifull God) to forgiue vs all our vnthankfulneſſe, vnkindneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13612:25"/> prophanes, and great abuſing of all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſpecially our abuſe and contempt of thy Goſpell, togither with all other the ſins of our life which we confes are inumerable, &amp; mo then can be reckoned vp both in omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good things, and commiſſion of euill. We moſt humbly intreate thée to ſet them al ouer to that reckoning which thy ſon Chriſt hath made vp for them vpon his croſſe, and neuer to lay any of them to our charge, but fréely forget all and forgiue all. Naile downe all our ſinnes and iniquities to the Croſſe of Chriſt burie them in his death, bath them in his bloude, hide them in his wounds, let them neuer riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs. Set vs frée of the miſeries that are vpon vs for ſin, &amp; kéepe back the iudgements to come, both of ſoule &amp; bodie, goods &amp; good name. Be reconciled vnto vs in thy deare ſonne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all matters paſt, not once remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring or repeating vnto vs our olde and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable iniquities: but accept vs as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in him, imputing his righteouſneſſe to vs, and our ſinnes to him. Let his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſatiſfie thy iuſtice for all our vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, his obedience for our diſobedience, his perfection for our imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer we humbly beſéech thy good maieſtie to giue vs the true ſight and féeling of our manifold
<pb facs="tcp:13612:26"/> ſinnes, that we may not be blinded in them through delight, or hardned in them through cuſtome, as the reprobates are, but that we may be euen weary of them, and much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for them, labouring &amp; ſtriuing by all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes to get out of them. Good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touch our harts with true repentance for all ſinne. Let vs not take any delight or pleaſure in any ſinne: but howſoeuer we fal through frailtie (as we fall often) yet let vs neuer fall finally, let vs neuer lie downe in ſinne, nor continue in ſinne: but let vs get vpon our féete agayne, and turne to thée with all our hearts, and ſéeke thée whilſt thou mayeſt be founde, and whilſt thou doſt offer grace and mercie vnto vs. O Lord encreaſe in vs that true and liuely fayth whereby we may lay ſure hold on thy ſonne Chriſt, and reſt vpon his merites altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Giue vs fayth aſſuredly to beléeue all the great and pretious promiſes made in the Goſpell, and ſtrengthen vs from aboue to walke and abound in all the true and ſound fruites of fayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vs walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirite. Let vs féele the power of thy ſonnes death killing ſinne in our mortall bodies, and the power of his reſurrection, rayſing vs vp to newneſſe of life. Let vs growe daylie in the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:13612:26"/> of the ſpirite, and the mortification of the fleſh. Let vs liue holily, iuſtly, and ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent euill world, ſhewing foorth the vertues of thée in all our particular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that we may adorne our moſt holy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, &amp; ſhine as lights in the midſt of a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, &amp; froward generation amongſt whom we liue, being gainefull to all by our liues &amp; conuerſations, &amp; offenſiue to none. To this end we pray thée fill vs with thy ſpirite and al ſpirituall graces: as loue, wiſedome, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, contentment, méekenes, humility, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancy, chaſtity, kindenes, and affability, &amp; ſtir vs vp to vſe prayer &amp; watchfulnes, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; meditation in thy lawe, and al other good meanes whereby we may grow and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in all heauenly vertues. Bleſſe vs in the vſe of the meanes, from day to day: make vs ſuch as thou wouldeſt haue vs to bée, and ſuch as wée deſire to bée, working in vs both will and déede, purpoſe and power. For thou, O Lorde, art all in all, thou wilt haue mercie vppon whom thou wilt haue mercy, and whom thou wilt thou hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. Haue mercie vppon vs therefore (deare Father) and neuer leaue vs to our ſelues, nor to our owne wils, luſts, &amp; deſires, but aſſiſt vs with thy good ſpirite, that wée may continue to the end in a righteous
<pb facs="tcp:13612:27"/> courſe: that ſo at length we may be receiued into glory, &amp; be pertakers of that immortall crowne which thou haſt laid vp for all that loue thée, and truely call vpon thée.</p>
            <p>Further, we intreat thée, O heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to giue vs all things neceſſary for this life: as foode, raimcut, health, peace, liberty, &amp; ſuch fréedome from thoſe many fold miſeries which we lie open vnto euery day, as thou ſéeſt méete. Bleſſe vnto vs all the meanes which thou haſt put into our hands for the ſuſtenance of this fraile life. Bleſſe our ſtock, and ſtore, corne, &amp; cattle, trades, &amp; occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; all the workes of our handes: for thy bleſſing onely maketh rich, and it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſorrows with it. Giue vs therfore ſuch a competencie &amp; ſufficiencie of theſe outward bleſſings, as thou in thy heauenly wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſéeſt moſt néedful for vs. Grant theſe things good father to vs here preſent, &amp; to al thine abſent: praying thée in ſpeciall fauour to remember our frinds, &amp; kinſfolks in the fleſh, al our good neighbours, &amp; welwillers, &amp; al thoſe for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are bound to pray by nature, by deſerts, or any duty whatſoeuer, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our only mediator, to whom with thée and the holy Ghoſt, be giuen al praiſe &amp; glory, both now, and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:27"/>
            <head rend="italic">An Euening prayer, to be vſed in priuate families.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall God, and our moſt louing, &amp; deare Father, we thy vnworthy children doe here fall downe at the foote of thy great maieſty, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging from our harts, that we are altogeather vnworthy to come néere thée, or to look towards thée, becauſe thou art a God of infinite glory, and we are moſt vile, and abhominable ſinners, ſuch as were concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and borne in ſinne and corruption, fuch as haue inherited our fathers corruptions, and alſo haue actually tranſgreſſed all thy holy ſtatutes, and lawes, both in thoughts, wordes, and déedes, before we knew thée: and ſince, ſecretly and openly, with our ſelues, and with others, our particular ſinnes are moe then can be numbred: for who knoweth how often times he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. But this we muſt néedes confeſſe againſt our ſelues, that our hartes are full of pride, couetouſneſſe, and the loue of this world, full of wrath, anger, and impatiencie, full of lying, diſſembling, and deceiuing, full of vanity, hardneſſe, and prophaneneſſe, full of infidelity, diſtruſt
<pb facs="tcp:13612:28"/> and ſelfe-loue, full of luſt, vncleaneneſſe, and al abhominable deſires, yea our harts are the very ſinks of ſinne, and dunghils of all filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And beſides all this, we doe omitte the good things we ſhould doe: for there are in vs great wantes of faith, of loue, of zeale of patience, of contentment, and of euery good grace: ſo as thou haſt iuſt cauſe to procéede to ſentence of iudgement againſt vs, as moſt damnable tranſgreſſors of all thy holy commaundements; yea ſuch as are ſunke in our rebellions, and haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, and often committed high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt thy maieſtie, and therefore thou maieſt iuſtly caſt vs all downe into hell fire, there to be tormented with Sathan, and his angelles for euer. And we haue nothing to except againſt thy maieſty for ſo doing, ſith therein thou ſhouldeſt deale with vs but according to equity, and our iuſt deſerts. Wherefore deare Father, we doe appeale from thy iuſtice to thy mercie, moſt humbly intreating thée to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon vs, and fréely to forgiue vs all our ſinnes paſt whatſoeuer, both new, and olde, ſecret, and open, knowne and vnknowne, and that for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our onely Mediator. And we pray thée touch our harts with true griefe, and vnfained repentance
<pb facs="tcp:13612:28"/> for them, that they may be a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſorrow, and hart ſmart vnto vs, ſo as nothing may gréeue vs more than this, that we haue offended thée being our ſpeciall friend and father. Giue vs therefore (deare Father) euery day more and more ſight and féeling of our ſinnes, with true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation vnder the ſame. Giue vs alſo that true and liuely faith, whereby we may laie ſure hold on thy Sonne Chriſt, and all his merites, applying the ſame to our owne ſoules; ſo as we may ſtand fully perſwaded that whatſoeuer hee hath done vppon the croſſe, he hath done for vs particularly, as well as for others. Giue vs faith (good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) conſtantly to beléeue all the ſwéete promiſes of the Goſpell, touching remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne, and eternall life, made in thy ſonne Chriſt. O Lord increaſe our faith, that we may altogether reſt vpon thy promiſes which are all yea, &amp; Amen. Yea, that we may ſettle our ſelues and all that we haue wholy vpon them: both our ſoules, bodies, goods, name, wiues, children and our whole eſtate: knowing that all things depend vpon thy promiſes, power, and prouidence, and that thy word doth ſupport, and beare vp the whole order of nature. Moreouer, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thée, O Lord, to ſtrengthen vs from
<pb facs="tcp:13612:29"/> aboue to walke in euery good waye, and to bring foorth the fruits of true faith in all our particular actions, ſtudying to pleaſe thée in all things &amp; to be fruitfull in all good works; that we may ſhew foorth vnto all men by our good conuerſation whoſe children we are: and that we may adorne and beautifie our moſt holy profeſſion by walking in a Chriſtian courſe, and in all the ſound fruits, and practiſe of godlineſſe, and true religion. To this end we pray thée ſanctifie our harts by thy ſpirite yet more, and more: ſanctifie our ſoules and bodies and all our corrupt naturall faculties, as reaſon, vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will, and affections, ſo as they may be fitted for thy worſhip, and ſeruice, taking a delight and pleaſure therein. Stir vs vp ſo vſe prayer, watchfulnes, reading &amp; medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thy lawe, and all other good meanes, whereby we may profit in grace &amp; goodnes from day to day. Bleſſe vs in the vſe of the meanes, that we may daily die to ſin, &amp; liue to righteouſneſſe. Draw vs yet nearer vnto thée: help vs againſt our manifold wants. Amend our great imperfections, renue vs inwardly more and more, repaire the ruines of our harts: aide vs againſt the remnants of ſinne. Enlarge our hearts to run the way of thy commandements. Direct all our ſteps
<pb facs="tcp:13612:29"/> in thy worde: let none iniquitie haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer vs. Aſſiſt vs againſt our ſpeciall infirmities, and maſter ſinnes, that we may get the victorie ouer them all, to thy glory, &amp; the great peace &amp; comfort of our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Strengthen vs good father by thy grace &amp; holy ſpirit againſt the common cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the world, as pride, whoredome, couetouſnes, contempt of thy Goſpell, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, lying, diſſembling, &amp; deceiuing. O dear father, let vs not be ouercome of theſe filthy vices, nor any other ſinfull pleaſures, &amp; fond delights, wherewith thouſands are carried headlong to deſtruction. Arme our ſoules againſt all the temptations of this worlde, the fleſh, and the diuell, that we may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them all through thy helpe, and kéepe on the right way to life, that we may liue in thy feare, and die in thy fauour, that our laſt dayes may be our beſt dayes, and that we may end in great peace of conſcience. Grant theſe things good Father, and all other néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full graces for our ſoules, or bodies, or any of thine throughout the whole world, for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſts ſake. In whoſe name we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call vpon thée as he hath taught vs in his Goſpel, ſaying: <hi rend="roman">Our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13612:30"/>
            <head rend="roman">A prayer to be vſed at any time, by one alone priuately.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Lord my God, &amp; heauenly Father, I thy moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy childe, do here in thy ſight fréely confeſſe that I am a moſt ſinful creature, &amp; damnable tranſgreſſor of all thy holy laws &amp; commaundements: that as I was borne &amp; bred in ſin, &amp; ſtained in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe, ſo haue I continually brought ſorth the corrupt &amp; vgly fruites of that infection, and contagion, wherein I was firſt conceiued both in thoughts, words, &amp; workes. If I ſhould go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to recken vp my particular offences, I know not where to begin, or where to make an end. For they are moe then the haires of my head, yea far mo then I can poſſibly féele or know. For who knoweth the height, and depth of his corruption? who knoweth how ofthe offendeth? Thou only O Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my ſinnes, who knoweſt my heart: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is hid from thée: thou knoweſt what I haue béene, and what I am; yea my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth accuſe me of many, and grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous euilles, I do daylie féele by wofull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periene how fraile I am, how prone to euill, and how vntoward to all goodneſſe. My minde is full of vainity, my hart full of
<pb facs="tcp:13612:30"/> prophaneneſſe, mine affections full of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, dulneſſe, &amp; drowſineſſe in matters of thy worſhip &amp; ſeruice. Yea, my whole ſoule is full of ſpirituall blindneſſe, hardneſſe, vnprofitableneſſe, coldneſſe, and ſecurity. And in very déede I am altogether a lumpe of ſinne, and a maſſe of all miſery: and therefore I haue forfeited thy fauour, and incurred thy high diſpleaſure, and haue giuen thée iuſt cauſe to frowne vpon me, to giue me ouer, and leaue me to mine owne corrupt will and affections. But (O my deare Father) I haue learned from thy mouth that thou art a God full of mercy, ſlow to wrath, and of great compaſſion, and kindeneſſe, towardes all ſuch as grone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of their ſinnes. Therefore extend thy great mercie towardes me poore ſinner, and giue me a generall pardon for all mine offences whatſoeuer: ſeale it in the blood of thy ſonne, and ſeale it to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by thy ſpirite, aſſuring mee more and more, of thy loue and fauour towards me, and that thou art a reconciled father vnto me. Graunt that I may in al time to come, loue thée much, becauſe much is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and of very loue feare thée, and obey thée. O Lord increaſe my faith, that I may ſtedfaſtly beléeue all the promiſes of the
<pb facs="tcp:13612:31"/> Goſpell made in thy ſon Chriſt, and reſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them altogether: enable me to bring forth the ſound fruites of faith and repentance in all my perticuler actions. Fill my ſoule full of ioy, and peace in beléeuing. Fill me full of inward comfort and ſpirituall ſtrength againſt al temptations: giue me yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter féeling of thy loue and many folde mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towardes me, worke in my ſoule a loue of thy Maieſty, a zeale of thy glory, an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of euil, and a deſire of all good things. Giue me victory ouer thoſe ſinnes which thou knoweſt are ſtrongeſt in me. Let me once at laſt make a conqueſt of the worlde, and the fleſh. Mortifie in me whatſoeuer is carnal, ſanctifie me throughout by thy ſpirit, knit my heart to thée for euer that I may feare thy name, renew in me the image of thy ſonne Chriſt daylie more and more. Giue me a delight in the reading &amp; medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy word. Let me reioyce in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique miniſtrie thereof. Let me loue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence all the faithfull miniſters of thy Goſpel. Sanctifie their doctrines to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſeale them in my ſoule, write them in my heart, giue me a ſoft and melting heart, that I may tremble at thy wordes, and be alwayes much affected with Godly ſermons. Let not my ſinnes hold backe thy
<pb facs="tcp:13612:31"/> mercies from me, nor mine vnworthyneſſe ſtoppe the paſſage of thy grace. Open mine eyes to ſée that great wonders of thy Law. Reueale thy ſecrets vnto me, be open har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards me thy vnworthy ſeruant. Hide nothing from me that may make for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the good of my ſoule. Bleſſe all meanes vnto me which thou vſeſt for my good. Bleſſe all holy inſtructions to my ſoule. Bleſſe me at all times both in hearing and reading thy word: Giue me the right vſe of all thy mercies, &amp; corrections, that I may be the better for them. Let me abound in loue to thy children. Let my heart be very néerely knit vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that where thou loueſt moſt there I may loue moſt alſo. Let me watch &amp; pray, that I enter not into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: giue me patience and contentment in all things. Let me loue thée more and more, and the world leſſe and leſſe. So drawe my minde vpward, that I may deſpiſe all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things. Let me be ſo wrapt and rauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſight &amp; féeling of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things, that I may make a baſe reckoning of all carthly things. Let me vſe this world as though I vſed it not. Let me vſe it but for neceſſity, as meate and drinke. Let me not be carried away with the vaine pleaſures and fond delights therof. Good father worke
<pb facs="tcp:13612:32"/> thy good worke in me, and neuer leaue me, nor forſake me, till thou haſt brought me to true happineſſe. Oh deare Father make me faithful in my calling, that I may ſerue thée in it, and be alwaies carefull to do what good I may in any thing. Bleſſe me in my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate. Bleſſe my ſoule, body, goods, and name. Bleſſe all that belongeth vnto me. Bleſſe my goings out, and commings in. Let thy countenance be lifted vp vpon me, now and alwayes: cheare me vp with the ioyes and comforts of thy ſpirite, make me thankefull for all thy mercies. For I muſt néeds confeſſe that thou art very kinde vnto me in all things. For in thée I liue, mooue, and haue my béeing: of thée I haue my welfare and good béeing, thou art a dayly friend, and ſpecial good Benefactor vnto me. I liue at thy coſt and charges. I hold all of thée in Chiefe, and I finde that thou art ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wearie of doing me good: thy goodneſſe towardes me is vnſtanchable. Oh I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be thankefull inough vnto thée for al thy mercies both ſpirituall and corporall. But in ſuch meaſure as I am able I praiſe thy name for all, beſéeching thée to accept of my thankeſgiuing in thy Sonne Chriſt, and to giue me a profitable vſe of all thy fauours, that thereby my hart may be fully drawne
<pb facs="tcp:13612:32"/> vnto thée: giue me O Father to be of ſuch a good nature, and diſpoſition, that I may be wonne by gentleneſſe, and fayre meanes, as much as if thou gaueſt me many laſhes. Pardon all mine vnthankefulneſſe, vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and great abuſing of thy mercies, and giue me grace to vſe them more to thy glory in all time to come. Strengthen me deare Father thus to continue praiſing and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thy name here vpon earth, that after this life I may be crowned of thée for euer in thy kingdome. Graunt theſe petitions moſt mercifull God, not onely to me, but to all thy deare children throughout the whole world, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake in whoſe name I doe further call vpon thée, ſaying as hée hath taught me. <hi rend="roman">O our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer rend="roman">FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
